<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>freenode news</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/atom.xml" rel="alternate"></link><id>https://freenode.net/news/atom.xml</id><updated>2017-07-24T15:04:39+00:00</updated><entry><title>freenode at DEFCON25</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/defcon" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-24T15:04:39+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-24T15:04:39+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-07-24:/news/defcon</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="defcon25-takes-place-at-caesars-palace-in-las-vegas-on-27-30-of-this-month-freenode-will-be-therewill-you"&gt;DEFCON25 takes place at Caesar's Palace in Las Vegas on 27-30 of this month. freenode will be there—will you?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, freenode will have a booth in the vendor village—come have a chat with us, grab some stickers or get your hands on a limited edition freenode t-shirt!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="freenode-live-october-28-29th-2017"&gt;freenode #live - October 28-29th 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only a few more days to lock in to the special early bird ticket price! Get your &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/tickets"&gt;tickets now&lt;/a&gt;, and don't forget to make a CFP submission if you fancy giving a talk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned, we're excited to be announcing the keynote speakers in the next few days!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Exhibiting at freenode #live</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live-exhibit" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-18T09:29:50+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-18T09:29:50+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-07-18:/news/freenode-live-exhibit</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You might have seen our &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live"&gt;latest blog post&lt;/a&gt;, where we announced the registration and call for participation for the freenode #live conference that takes place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on October 28-29th this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The freenode network plays host to a variety of free and open source software and other peer-directed projects. We would love to see your project come exhibit at freenode #live and we invite you to e-mail us at exhibit@freenode.live if you are interested in coming along to showcase your project and meet like-minded FOSS enthusiasts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to ensure that the freenode #live conference remains affordable and accessible to the entire community, and to that end there is no exhibition charge for nonprofits and unincorporated FOSS projects. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You might have seen our &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live"&gt;latest blog post&lt;/a&gt;, where we announced the registration and call for participation for the freenode #live conference that takes place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on October 28-29th this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The freenode network plays host to a variety of free and open source software and other peer-directed projects. We would love to see your project come exhibit at freenode #live and we invite you to e-mail us at exhibit@freenode.live if you are interested in coming along to showcase your project and meet like-minded FOSS enthusiasts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to ensure that the freenode #live conference remains affordable and accessible to the entire community, and to that end there is no exhibition charge for nonprofits and unincorporated FOSS projects. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we are taking a grassroots approach with our conference, this does not mean that there is no space for corporate exhibitors and we recognise that the conference may provide opportunities for you too, and we would also like to welcome you to drop us a line to find out about our corporate exhibition packages or to tailor one specific to your company. Prices remain low also for corporate entities and we would love to see both types of exhibitor in Bristol on October 28 and 29th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can register and submit a response to our CFP &lt;a href="https:///freenode.live"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and we hope to start announcing keynote speakers and exhibitors soon. Please do keep an eye on the website though, we will also be opening up for nominations shortly as we will be presenting two awards as part of freenode #live, including the Rob Levin Memorial Community Award! Perhaps you know someone who has made great contributions to your community, or even a project that has redefined the community spirit in a positive way? Have a think about who YOU will be nominating! &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>freenode #live - Registration and CFP now open</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-13T19:35:39+00:00</published><updated>2017-07-13T19:35:39+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-07-13:/news/freenode-live</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The inaugural freenode #live conference takes place at At-Bristol in Bristol, UK from Saturday 28 to Sunday 29 October 2017. Both days will include talks and workshops, and we look forward to this community-focused gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/tickets"&gt;Tickets are now on sale and there is a special Early Bird price until 31 July&lt;/a&gt; and we are also taking &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/program/proposal/new"&gt;submissions&lt;/a&gt; for the call for participation, we have three tracks to choose from (FOSS &amp;amp; Community, Privacy &amp;amp; Security and Making &amp;amp; Remixing) and we look forward to receiving your submission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be making every effort to ensure that freenode #live is as inclusive an event as is possible and we encourage the minorities within our community to attend and to submit proposals.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The inaugural freenode #live conference takes place at At-Bristol in Bristol, UK from Saturday 28 to Sunday 29 October 2017. Both days will include talks and workshops, and we look forward to this community-focused gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/tickets"&gt;Tickets are now on sale and there is a special Early Bird price until 31 July&lt;/a&gt; and we are also taking &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/program/proposal/new"&gt;submissions&lt;/a&gt; for the call for participation, we have three tracks to choose from (FOSS &amp;amp; Community, Privacy &amp;amp; Security and Making &amp;amp; Remixing) and we look forward to receiving your submission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be making every effort to ensure that freenode #live is as inclusive an event as is possible and we encourage the minorities within our community to attend and to submit proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-are-we-looking-for"&gt;What are we looking for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are looking for proposals for talks, workshops and other events and as a community-focused organisation, freenode is committed to ensuring that this conference is open to YOUR ideas! The more varied the programme, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you have something you would like to share with the community? We welcome proposals on all subjects and at any level of technical expertise, please do not feel constrained by the track subjects. We are keen to hear about your experiments, your discoveries, solutions, achievements and even your failures. We want to hear about “how to get started with X,” “how to use Y,” and “what we learned from working on Z”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want you to come teach us something new, we want you to make us think and we want you to make us laugh. Go ahead and submit a proposal for a talk, we’d love to hear your ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you could lead a tutorial on something of relevance to the freenode communities or the FOSS ecosystem? Why not throw your ideas in the hat and submit a proposal to hold a workshop?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a completely different idea? Is there something you would love to see happen at freenode #live? Let us know! We’re open to all ideas!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to hear from you, if you are planning to come to the event then you are very much part of the community and as such this is very much your conference. We want to hear from you regardless of whether you are a seasoned speaker or if this is the first time you are considering getting up in front of an audience. The freenode community is friendly and welcoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CFP closes on 15 August 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with our main sponsor and co-host of this year’s event, &lt;a href="https://www.privateinternetaccess.com"&gt;Private Internet Access&lt;/a&gt;, we very much look forward to welcoming you all to Bristol in October!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to drop us a line to 2017-team@freenode.live or hop into #live and chat with us.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Policy Updates</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/fn-policy" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-29T11:26:04+00:00</published><updated>2017-06-29T11:26:04+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-06-29:/news/fn-policy</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When the website was redesigned back in 2016, we made the decision to publish very limited policy for a period to allow us a chance to review our policies and guidelines, most of which were written over a decade ago. We have now completed our review and updated the &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/policies"&gt;policies&lt;/a&gt; accordingly. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When the website was redesigned back in 2016, we made the decision to publish very limited policy for a period to allow us a chance to review our policies and guidelines, most of which were written over a decade ago. We have now completed our review and updated the &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/policies"&gt;policies&lt;/a&gt; accordingly. &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>PIA and freenode joining forces</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/pia-fn" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-12T20:03:34+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-12T20:03:34+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-04-12:/news/pia-fn</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am incredibly excited to be able to share some amazing news with you today.
For the last few years, Private Internet Access has been a dedicated supporter
of the freenode project and we are delighted to be able to announce that
freenode is now officially part of the PIA family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;freenode has been providing services to Free and Open Source Software projects,
peer-directed projects and other projects that have a broadly licensed output
for the past 18 years, and there is a great deal of overlap between the visions
and missions of the two organisations, as well as the projects and
organisations the two organisations have supported, albeit in very different
ways over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob (lilo) founded freenode with the aim of providing a useful service to Free
and Open Source Software communities, peer-directed projects and others and I
think he would be proud of the growth we have experienced over the years if he
were still here to see it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am incredibly excited to be able to share some amazing news with you today.
For the last few years, Private Internet Access has been a dedicated supporter
of the freenode project and we are delighted to be able to announce that
freenode is now officially part of the PIA family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;freenode has been providing services to Free and Open Source Software projects,
peer-directed projects and other projects that have a broadly licensed output
for the past 18 years, and there is a great deal of overlap between the visions
and missions of the two organisations, as well as the projects and
organisations the two organisations have supported, albeit in very different
ways over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob (lilo) founded freenode with the aim of providing a useful service to Free
and Open Source Software communities, peer-directed projects and others and I
think he would be proud of the growth we have experienced over the years if he
were still here to see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I took over freenode following his death, my personal circumstances were
very different from what they are now. I had time—oodles of it—and volunteering
for freenode was very much a pleasure (by all means, it still is! Otherwise I
wouldn't be here). However, over the years, times changed, the project grew,
demands grew, my own responsibilities changed, both professionally and
personally and I, along with several other senior freenode volunteers, found
that we no longer had quite the same amount of time and energy to dedicate to
the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following discussion and deliberation we have decided to formally (and
legally) ally ourselves with PIA. Freenode will continue to operate as a
not-for-profit entity under the same management, with the same principles,
but PIA's involvement going forwards will provide us with opportunities and
resources that we could previously only dream of. PIA will provide an operating
budget, mentorship and support that will allow freenode to implement some of
the projects and ideas that have previously been on the backburner due to
constraints in terms of volunteer time and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-what-is-the-incentive-for-pia"&gt;Why? What is the incentive for PIA?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private Internet Access is committed to bringing the internet back to its
original state, where being online meant being in your own private world,
exploring, learning and creating. PIA is serious about supporting organisations
and individuals that it considers to be in alignment with its mission and
freenode is one such project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founders of PIA feel that freenode has helped a number of open source
projects progress, that freenode helps the community produce the pieces that
make the internet work smoothly, piece by piece, and that it empowers people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For PIA, this is about giving back, giving back to freenode and to the
communities that they consider vital to their success and to their mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The freenode project would be nothing without its communities. All of our
volunteers come from projects that use freenode, projects we are passionate
about and projects we want to see continue to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the PIA family, we can guarantee that the freenode project will
continue to operate and that we will have the support and resources to further
improve the services that we offer to FOSS communities and others, doing our
bit to ensure that you can all continue doing what you do best—making the
internet and the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-next"&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be few noticeable changes in terms of day-to-day operations, the
freenode project will continue to operate with much the same structure and
volunteer base as it does now. We anticipate that group registration will
become a quicker process and we look forward to implementing and announcing new
features in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, I have joined PIA as a full-time employee and I will be
holding a dual role. I will continue to head up the freenode project and you
will no doubt see and hear more of me as my availability and involvement
increases. Some of you might also find yourselves dealing with me in my new
role as Director of Sponsorship and Events at Private Internet Access, where I
will be heading up the work we undertake to support organisations, campaigns
and events globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you may bump into me at various conferences throughout the
year, and if you do, please do come have a chat—whether about PIA, freenode or
the weather!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the subject of conferences, I am also extremely happy to announce that
freenode #live will be taking place at At-Bristol in Bristol, UK on 28-29th
October 2017. We will shortly be making a separate announcement as we open up
registration and call for papers and I look forward to seeing you there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please do not hesitate to drop me a line (&lt;code&gt;/msg christel&lt;/code&gt;) on IRC if you
have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do keep an eye out for more exciting news!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Django AMA</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/django-ama" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-17T17:55:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-17T17:55:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Swant</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-02-17:/news/django-ama</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Start thinking of tricky questions!
Once again &lt;a href="http://freenode.net/news/community"&gt;the freenode community team&lt;/a&gt;
is pleased to announce another Ask Me Anything (AMA). This time &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;
will be our guest. Read more about them in the
&lt;a href="http://freenode.net/news/django-and-freenode"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; published last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is your chance to ask Django all your questions about them:
How do they utilize freenode? How can you contribute? And just who are these
Django Girls we've heard so much about? Anything that you would be interested
in learning about them, here's your opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMA is scheduled to take place on Wed Feb 22 18:00:00 UTC, 2017,
so grab your calendar and make sure you don't miss it.
You can watch the AMA in #freenode-ama and participate by asking questions
in #freenode-ama-questions during the session. In the meantime be sure to
visit their channel, #django, and get a head start on everyone else!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Start thinking of tricky questions!
Once again &lt;a href="http://freenode.net/news/community"&gt;the freenode community team&lt;/a&gt;
is pleased to announce another Ask Me Anything (AMA). This time &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;
will be our guest. Read more about them in the
&lt;a href="http://freenode.net/news/django-and-freenode"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; published last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is your chance to ask Django all your questions about them:
How do they utilize freenode? How can you contribute? And just who are these
Django Girls we've heard so much about? Anything that you would be interested
in learning about them, here's your opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMA is scheduled to take place on Wed Feb 22 18:00:00 UTC, 2017,
so grab your calendar and make sure you don't miss it.
You can watch the AMA in #freenode-ama and participate by asking questions
in #freenode-ama-questions during the session. In the meantime be sure to
visit their channel, #django, and get a head start on everyone else!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope to hold more Ask Me Anything sessions in the future. If this is
something your project would be interested in, please reach out to us
in #freenode-community or at &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Django and freenode</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/django-and-freenode" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-08T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-08T20:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Tim Graham (timograham)</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-02-08:/news/django-and-freenode</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For nearly twelve years, the &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django Project&lt;/a&gt;
has endeavoured to improve "the web framework for perfectionists with
deadlines." Django is a high-level Python Web framework that encourage
rapid development and clean, pragmatic design. Built by experienced
developers, it takes care of much of the hassle of Web development,
so you can focus on writing your app without needing to reinvent the
wheel. Of course, it's free and open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m contracted full-time by the Django Software Foundation
&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/fundraising/#fellowship-program"&gt;as a fellow&lt;/a&gt;,
to manage some of the administrative and community management tasks of
the Django project to support rapid development of Django itself. The
fellowship program has a major positive impact on how Django is
developed and maintained, and I’d encourage any large open source
project to consider a similar program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Django community is vibrant across the globe, with many annual
conferences and local meetups. Sprints are often held at these events,
but Django’s development is mainly coordinated remotely, so good
communication tools are important to us.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For nearly twelve years, the &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django Project&lt;/a&gt;
has endeavoured to improve "the web framework for perfectionists with
deadlines." Django is a high-level Python Web framework that encourage
rapid development and clean, pragmatic design. Built by experienced
developers, it takes care of much of the hassle of Web development,
so you can focus on writing your app without needing to reinvent the
wheel. Of course, it's free and open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m contracted full-time by the Django Software Foundation
&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/fundraising/#fellowship-program"&gt;as a fellow&lt;/a&gt;,
to manage some of the administrative and community management tasks of
the Django project to support rapid development of Django itself. The
fellowship program has a major positive impact on how Django is
developed and maintained, and I’d encourage any large open source
project to consider a similar program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Django community is vibrant across the globe, with many annual
conferences and local meetups. Sprints are often held at these events,
but Django’s development is mainly coordinated remotely, so good
communication tools are important to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-django-uses-freenode"&gt;How Django uses freenode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our community support channels include #django and the
&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/django-users"&gt;django-users mailing list&lt;/a&gt;.
Discussions about the development of Django itself are held
in #django-dev and the
&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/django-developers"&gt;django-developers mailing list&lt;/a&gt;. #django-sprint
provides a chat for sprint participants, including those who want to
join remotely. Finally, private discussions of the Django team are held
in the #django-core channel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep our community safe and welcoming, Django's
&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/conduct/"&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt; applies to
all spaces managed by the Django project or Django Software Foundation
(DSF). This includes IRC, the mailing lists, the issue tracker, DSF
events, and any other forums created by the project team which the
community uses for communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-next-for-django"&gt;What's next for Django?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're currently working toward releasing Django 1.11, our next
long-term support release, in April. This will be the last version of
Django to support Python 2.7. Meanwhile, Django's master development
branch is targeting Django 2.0 and will support Python 3 only. More
details are available on &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/download/#supported-versions"&gt;our roadmap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in learning more about Django,
&lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/stable/intro/tutorial01/"&gt;try our tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.
If you’re already a Django user and want to start contributing, our
documentation is extensive, including
&lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/internals/contributing/new-contributors/"&gt;advice for new contributors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Fedora AMA</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/fedora-ama" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-21T15:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-21T15:24:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Nathan Handler (nhandler)</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-01-21:/news/fedora-ama</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="community"&gt;freenode Community Team&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce a new
opportunity to learn about one of our many groups on freenode.
Justin W. Flory (jflory7) from the Fedora project has agreed to follow-up on
his recent &lt;a href="celebrating-fedora-freenode"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; with an "Ask Me
Anything" (AMA) session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who might not be familiar with an AMA, as its name suggests,
it is an opportunity for you to ask the Fedora project all of those questions
that you have been wondering. You can ask about the project itself, how they
utilize freenode, ways to start contributing, or any other topics you might be
interested in learning more about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session is scheduled to take place on Wed Jan 25 18:00:00 UTC 2017.
You can watch the AMA in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-ama&lt;/code&gt; and participate by asking questions in
&lt;code&gt;#freenode-ama-questions&lt;/code&gt; during the session.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="community"&gt;freenode Community Team&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce a new
opportunity to learn about one of our many groups on freenode.
Justin W. Flory (jflory7) from the Fedora project has agreed to follow-up on
his recent &lt;a href="celebrating-fedora-freenode"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; with an "Ask Me
Anything" (AMA) session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who might not be familiar with an AMA, as its name suggests,
it is an opportunity for you to ask the Fedora project all of those questions
that you have been wondering. You can ask about the project itself, how they
utilize freenode, ways to start contributing, or any other topics you might be
interested in learning more about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session is scheduled to take place on Wed Jan 25 18:00:00 UTC 2017.
You can watch the AMA in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-ama&lt;/code&gt; and participate by asking questions in
&lt;code&gt;#freenode-ama-questions&lt;/code&gt; during the session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope to hold more Ask Me Anything sessions in the future. If this is something
your project would be interested in, please reach out to us in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-community&lt;/code&gt;
or at &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>New Year, New freenode</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/new-year-new-freenode" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-03T11:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-03T11:33:00+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2017-01-03:/news/new-year-new-freenode</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, not entirely new but we are about to embark upon a spot of maintenance
and some minor upgrades that could cause some disruption on the freenode
network as servers are being brought down for maintenance, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to apologise in advance and further updates will be provided by
way of global notices and wallops, depending on what we deem necessary for the
interventions concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your patience and understanding while we carry out the
maintenance and thank you for using freenode!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, not entirely new but we are about to embark upon a spot of maintenance
and some minor upgrades that could cause some disruption on the freenode
network as servers are being brought down for maintenance, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to apologise in advance and further updates will be provided by
way of global notices and wallops, depending on what we deem necessary for the
interventions concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your patience and understanding while we carry out the
maintenance and thank you for using freenode!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Happy New Year!</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/2016-is-finally-dead" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-31T09:46:58+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-31T09:46:58+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2016-12-31:/news/2016-is-finally-dead</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another year comes to an end: 2016, a year many will be glad to see the back
of. For many the year has been dominated by uncertainty, by fear, and by
sadness—a year dominated, in no small part, by the political shift on both
sides of the Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a year dominated by death. We have looked on in surprise as icon after icon
has passed away throughout the course of the year. We have looked on in sadness
as masses of people have succumbed to terror and war. We have looked on as
people try to flee, in search of a better life, often not succeeding. And as a
project based in the UK we look on as the government tries to do its best to
put an end to our digital rights, to our privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, freenode experienced a sudden influx of Arabic-speaking users.
They came out of nowhere and there were lots of them. Their arrival caused some
distress to the existing communities on the network at the time; freenode
predominantly caters to free and open source software developers and users and
we were all somewhat perplexed when our network was overrun by teenagers
wanting to chat about girls and football. They all seemed to be connecting from
Syria.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another year comes to an end: 2016, a year many will be glad to see the back
of. For many the year has been dominated by uncertainty, by fear, and by
sadness—a year dominated, in no small part, by the political shift on both
sides of the Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a year dominated by death. We have looked on in surprise as icon after icon
has passed away throughout the course of the year. We have looked on in sadness
as masses of people have succumbed to terror and war. We have looked on as
people try to flee, in search of a better life, often not succeeding. And as a
project based in the UK we look on as the government tries to do its best to
put an end to our digital rights, to our privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, freenode experienced a sudden influx of Arabic-speaking users.
They came out of nowhere and there were lots of them. Their arrival caused some
distress to the existing communities on the network at the time; freenode
predominantly caters to free and open source software developers and users and
we were all somewhat perplexed when our network was overrun by teenagers
wanting to chat about girls and football. They all seemed to be connecting from
Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Aleppo comes up in the news, many of us find ourselves thinking about those
kids and what happened to them. One of our volunteers invested a fair amount of
time trying to figure out where they ended up. When discussing it recently, he
shared his experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“After a few weeks of surreal crazy chaos we worked out that they were using a
Java IRC client - and internet café PCs - to connect to our system.  They
didn't know what it was for or why it existed but they'd found real-time
online communication for the first time and were enjoying the shit out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first used IRC in the 90s when an IRC client was given to me by a friend not
very long after it was the medium for some of the first ever real-time citizen
journalism during the 1991 Gulf War. In much the same way that someone threw
some software at me in a computing lab in Oxford and showed me how to use it
to chat, these kids were sharing and collaborating in the streets and using
new tools to talk to the guy a computer or a block or a neighbourhood over
with equal ease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we tried to shepherd a group of unruly teenagers into a corner where
they would cause less trouble for everyone else, I got to know a couple of the
better English-speakers quite well; they seemed mostly to be basically decent
kids growing up much too quickly and experiencing my corner of the internet
for the first time. They were mostly in Aleppo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Arab Spring progressed they grew in number and it was genuinely cool
watching them discover and explore. But as spring turned to summer and then
autumn, they gradually dropped in number and started to vanish. After a while
I realised they'd mostly gone, and I tried to track some of the stragglers
down to find out what had happened to the ringleader or any of the kids I'd
gotten to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ringleader had been killed in shellfire, was the answer. I found his blog.
It had been silent for a couple of months. Eventually it fell off the internet
when the account was suspended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a year later they all seemed to have gone I made more of an effort to do
some digital anthropology and figure out just what had happened to them in
more depth. I talked to a Lebanese peer who ran some adult Arabic language
discussion spaces and he speculated that by that point hey had all died or
fled and crossed the border into other countries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we reflect on the sobering condition of the world around us, it would be
easy to forget about the positives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have the privilege of seeing thousands of people work on thousands of
projects they love, and it's humbling and exciting to be allowed to play a small
part in each of them. We're extremely grateful for that: we love learning about
your projects; we love learning about the different ways in which people
communicate and collaborate; we love learning about what you produce and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have exceptionally generous sponsors who not only provide us with hardware
and bandwidth but also with their continued time and expertise when required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to one such sponsor we have also secured the majority of the requisite
funding to put on a two-day live conference which will take place in the UK in
August 2017. Further details and a formal announcement will follow early in the
New Year. We are incredibly excited and hope that you will join us; we'd love
for your project to exhibit or perhaps you could give a talk? Keep an eye out
for our announcement!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that, we would like to thank you all for using freenode and wish you the
very best for 2017!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Celebrating Fedora 25 with freenode</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/celebrating-fedora-freenode" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-21T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-21T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Justin W. Flory (jflory7)</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2016-12-21:/news/celebrating-fedora-freenode</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Celebrating Fedora 25 with freenode" src="../static/img/celebrating-fedora-freenode.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 22nd, 2016, the &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Overview"&gt;Fedora
Project&lt;/a&gt; released Fedora 25,
the latest and greatest version of our
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_kernel"&gt;Linux-based&lt;/a&gt; operating
system. For &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/archives/fedora-announce-list/2003-November/msg00000.html"&gt;over thirteen
years&lt;/a&gt;,
the Fedora community has worked to bring the leading edge of open source
development to the world. Fedora's focus is guided by its &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Foundations"&gt;Four
Foundations&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Freedom,
Friends, Features, First&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Freedom&lt;/em&gt; is representative of Fedora's
commitment to championing free and open source software and contributing
back to upstream projects for the benefit of the open source community.
&lt;em&gt;Features&lt;/em&gt; stands for Fedora's commitment to driving some of the newest
features &lt;em&gt;First&lt;/em&gt;. Some of these examples include the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayland_(display_server_protocol)"&gt;Wayland display
server&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Systemd"&gt;systemd&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNOME#GNOME_3"&gt;GNOME
3&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps most
importantly, &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; are for the friendships made by contributors from
around the world who help make every release of Fedora possible. Part of
why &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; is an important part of the Four Foundations is
communication. Fedora community members come from all over the planet,
including six out of seven continents. The tools we use to communicate
help us collaborate, solve problems, and build friendships. IRC and
freenode are an important part of how we communicate. Fedora registered
our first channel on freenode on December 29, 2002. As we celebrate
thirteen years of open source collaboration and the newest release of
Fedora 25, the Fedora community wanted to reflect on our longstanding
relationship with freenode.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Celebrating Fedora 25 with freenode" src="../static/img/celebrating-fedora-freenode.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 22nd, 2016, the &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Overview"&gt;Fedora
Project&lt;/a&gt; released Fedora 25,
the latest and greatest version of our
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_kernel"&gt;Linux-based&lt;/a&gt; operating
system. For &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/archives/fedora-announce-list/2003-November/msg00000.html"&gt;over thirteen
years&lt;/a&gt;,
the Fedora community has worked to bring the leading edge of open source
development to the world. Fedora's focus is guided by its &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Foundations"&gt;Four
Foundations&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Freedom,
Friends, Features, First&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Freedom&lt;/em&gt; is representative of Fedora's
commitment to championing free and open source software and contributing
back to upstream projects for the benefit of the open source community.
&lt;em&gt;Features&lt;/em&gt; stands for Fedora's commitment to driving some of the newest
features &lt;em&gt;First&lt;/em&gt;. Some of these examples include the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayland_(display_server_protocol)"&gt;Wayland display
server&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Systemd"&gt;systemd&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNOME#GNOME_3"&gt;GNOME
3&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps most
importantly, &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; are for the friendships made by contributors from
around the world who help make every release of Fedora possible. Part of
why &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; is an important part of the Four Foundations is
communication. Fedora community members come from all over the planet,
including six out of seven continents. The tools we use to communicate
help us collaborate, solve problems, and build friendships. IRC and
freenode are an important part of how we communicate. Fedora registered
our first channel on freenode on December 29, 2002. As we celebrate
thirteen years of open source collaboration and the newest release of
Fedora 25, the Fedora community wanted to reflect on our longstanding
relationship with freenode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-fedora-uses-freenode"&gt;How Fedora uses freenode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a large open source project, there are many different teams and
sub-projects in Fedora that help move us toward a new release. Just like
there are many parts to a car's engine, there are many parts to Fedora's
engine. Some of these groups are officially recognized sub-projects like
the &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Design"&gt;Design team&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/CommOps"&gt;Community
Operations&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Docs_Project"&gt;Docs
team&lt;/a&gt;. Other times, they
are informal &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Category:SIGs"&gt;Special Interest
Groups&lt;/a&gt; (SIGs) that bring
contributors together to focus on specific topics like programming
languages or desktop environments, like the &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/SIGs/Python"&gt;Python
SIG&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/SIGs/KDE"&gt;KDE
SIG&lt;/a&gt;. Usually, each of these
groups or teams will have their own IRC channel to coordinate in. The
Design team uses &lt;code&gt;#fedora-design&lt;/code&gt;, the Python SIG uses &lt;code&gt;#fedora-python&lt;/code&gt;…
and so on. In total, Fedora has over 175 registered channels to its
name. Frequently, teams will hold public meetings in the freenode
channels to work through tickets, plan ahead on upcoming tasks, or
discuss important topics for their team. There are a series of special
meeting channels used for this purpose. Using the
&lt;a href="http://meetbot.debian.net/Manual.html"&gt;MeetBot&lt;/a&gt; plugin, Fedora uses our
own &lt;a href="https://github.com/fedora-infra/supybot-fedora"&gt;zodbot&lt;/a&gt; to help run
meetings, mark up links or important ideas, and create a pretty HTML
summary at the end of the meeting. All of these summaries and full logs
are found at
&lt;a href="https://meetbot.fedoraproject.org/"&gt;meetbot.fedoraproject.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tips-to-using-irc-effectively"&gt;Tips to using IRC effectively&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are countless different workflows, IRC clients, and handy plugins
available to customize the IRC experience. In the spirit of the
&lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; Foundation and the Code of Conduct, Fedora contributors are
encouraged to &lt;a href="https://getfedora.org/code-of-conduct"&gt;always be excellent to one
another&lt;/a&gt;. It's important to
follow good manners in any IRC channel, Fedora or any other. Having good
manners in IRC are as important as it is in real life. Be courteous to
others, and if in doubt, it's good to assume the best intentions by
others. IRC is important for Fedora, and many contributors have put
together guides of our own as well. You can read more tips from the
Fedora team in our &lt;a href="https://fedoramagazine.org/beginners-guide-irc/"&gt;IRC Beginner's
Guide&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href="https://fedoramagazine.org/"&gt;Fedora
Magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-next-for-fedora"&gt;What's next for Fedora?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As 2016 comes to an end, we're wrapping up on our own new release of
Fedora 25. The Fedora community is looking forward to helping drive open
source innovation and contributing to the Linux community for many years
to come. Fedora currently has more than 2,000 contributors, and in the
tenth percentile of active contributors, 65% of them are from the
community (&lt;a href="https://mattdm.org/fedora/2016flock/StateofFedoraAugust2016-v160731a.pdf"&gt;State of Fedora, Flock
2016&lt;/a&gt;).
The Fedora steam engine is chugging ahead, and we're excited to see
where it takes us next. We're happy to be able to have shared past,
current, and future milestones together with the freenode community.
Keep an eye out for Fedora Ambassadors in Europe during
&lt;a href="https://devconf.cz/"&gt;DevConf&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2017/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt;.
You can also find us in North America at &lt;a href="https://brickhack.io/"&gt;BrickHack
2017&lt;/a&gt;. And there will be more events all through
the year you can keep an eye out for us at!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>A brief security update from the infrastructure team</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/PSA-brief-update-infra" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-20T05:30:34+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-20T05:30:34+00:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2016-12-20:/news/PSA-brief-update-infra</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A freenode volunteer has identified and responded to a suspected compromise of their e-mail accounts, which could have provided 
an unauthorised user with limited access to some data sent via internal e-mail systems (this could include support tickets or 
internal communications).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, we instigated audit procedures immediately so as to ensure the security of the production network and accompanying 
infrastructure. The investigation is ongoing, but at this time we have no reason to believe that any other unauthorised access 
was gained. Nevertheless, in the interests of transparency and security for our users, we wish to notify anyone who may have 
been affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, we would still recommend that you ensure that you change any passwords to freenode systems, and be alert to any 
suspicious activity on your account. We would additionally always recommend that you not share passwords between accounts, 
especially those spanning multiple providers (please ensure you have a registered e-mail address before changing your password 
so that it can be reset!).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A freenode volunteer has identified and responded to a suspected compromise of their e-mail accounts, which could have provided 
an unauthorised user with limited access to some data sent via internal e-mail systems (this could include support tickets or 
internal communications).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, we instigated audit procedures immediately so as to ensure the security of the production network and accompanying 
infrastructure. The investigation is ongoing, but at this time we have no reason to believe that any other unauthorised access 
was gained. Nevertheless, in the interests of transparency and security for our users, we wish to notify anyone who may have 
been affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, we would still recommend that you ensure that you change any passwords to freenode systems, and be alert to any 
suspicious activity on your account. We would additionally always recommend that you not share passwords between accounts, 
especially those spanning multiple providers (please ensure you have a registered e-mail address before changing your password 
so that it can be reset!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will provide further updates if it becomes appropriate to do so; please rest assured that we take the security and privacy 
of our users very seriously, and work with industry experts and law enforcement where appropriate to investigate and respond 
to possible security breaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>freenode Community Team</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/community" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-18T21:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-18T21:34:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Swant</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2016-10-18:/news/community</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not be aware that freenode has a dedicated community team and that we
would be delighted to help your projects get the most from freenode. The
freenode community team consists of christel, edk, JonathanD, mquin, Myrtti,
nhandler, Swant and tomaw, and we would love to help you spread the word about
releases and launches, conferences or events and any other project milestones
that may be of interest to our shared communities. We are happy to make
announcements on IRC, reshare your social media posts and we would love for you
to guest author or co-author a blog post for the freenode website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think this is something that would be useful for your project, please do
not hesitate to get in touch with us! You can find us in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-community&lt;/code&gt;
or drop us a line to &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not be aware that freenode has a dedicated community team and that we
would be delighted to help your projects get the most from freenode. The
freenode community team consists of christel, edk, JonathanD, mquin, Myrtti,
nhandler, Swant and tomaw, and we would love to help you spread the word about
releases and launches, conferences or events and any other project milestones
that may be of interest to our shared communities. We are happy to make
announcements on IRC, reshare your social media posts and we would love for you
to guest author or co-author a blog post for the freenode website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think this is something that would be useful for your project, please do
not hesitate to get in touch with us! You can find us in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-community&lt;/code&gt;
or drop us a line to &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure not to miss any interesting news by setting &lt;code&gt;/umode +w&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;/mode
yournick +w&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Resurrecting Tor, continued</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/tor-online" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-18T20:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-09-18T20:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>christel</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2016-09-18:/news/tor-online</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following an embarrassingly long period of no Tor support, we &lt;a href="resurrecting-tor"&gt;recently
blogged&lt;/a&gt; about resurrecting Tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of today, Tor users can once more connect to freenode over Tor; the hidden
service address is&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following an embarrassingly long period of no Tor support, we &lt;a href="resurrecting-tor"&gt;recently
blogged&lt;/a&gt; about resurrecting Tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of today, Tor users can once more connect to freenode over Tor; the hidden
service address is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;freenodeok2gncmy.onion
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hidden service requires SASL authentication, as before. In addition, due to
the abuse that led Tor access to be disabled in the first place, we have
unfortunately had to add another couple of restrictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must log in using SASL's &lt;code&gt;EXTERNAL&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;ECDSA-NIST256P-CHALLENGE&lt;/code&gt; (more
    below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you log out while connected via Tor, you will not be able to log in without
    reconnecting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't set up the requisite SASL authentication, we recommend SASL
EXTERNAL. You'll need to generate a client certificate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;openssl req -x509 -sha256 -new -newkey rsa:4096 -days 1000 -nodes -out freenode.pem -keyout freenode.pem
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and consult your IRC client's documentation to find out how to use it to
connect. Connect to freenode over TLS on the plain Internet and &lt;code&gt;/msg NickServ
CERT ADD&lt;/code&gt; to authorise it to your account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll then want to tell your client to try the &lt;code&gt;EXTERNAL&lt;/code&gt; mechanism. We lack
comprehensive documentation for this, but it's a feature in most modern
clients—check their docs for instructions for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's currently not possible to register an account for use with Tor without
connecting at least once over the Internet. We're investigating our options, and
would like to provide a solution to this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Resurrecting tor-sasl</title><link href="https://freenode.net/news/resurrecting-tor" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-05T16:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-09-05T16:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>edk</name></author><id>tag:freenode.net,2016-09-05:/news/resurrecting-tor</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As many of you will no doubt be aware, freenode used to run a Tor hidden
service, providing anonymous access to the network. Unfortunately, this had to
be disabled due to concerns about abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We regret that it has taken some time to resolve this issue but we are now
almost ready to deploy some software updates that will allow us to re-enable the
gateway. We've made one important change: password-based SASL authentication is
disabled over the Tor gateway, so you'll need to generate a client certificate
and add its fingerprint (&lt;code&gt;/msg NickServ CERT ADD&lt;/code&gt;) over a regular connection
before connecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'd appreciate your help testing this setup on &lt;a href="ircs://testnet.freenode.net:9003"&gt;our
testnet&lt;/a&gt;. Further instructions can be found
in &lt;code&gt;#freenode&lt;/code&gt; there. (if you already have a certificate set, the hidden
service is at
&lt;a href="ircs://testnet67chdulhs.onion:6697"&gt;ircs://testnet67chdulhs.onion:6697&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As many of you will no doubt be aware, freenode used to run a Tor hidden
service, providing anonymous access to the network. Unfortunately, this had to
be disabled due to concerns about abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We regret that it has taken some time to resolve this issue but we are now
almost ready to deploy some software updates that will allow us to re-enable the
gateway. We've made one important change: password-based SASL authentication is
disabled over the Tor gateway, so you'll need to generate a client certificate
and add its fingerprint (&lt;code&gt;/msg NickServ CERT ADD&lt;/code&gt;) over a regular connection
before connecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'd appreciate your help testing this setup on &lt;a href="ircs://testnet.freenode.net:9003"&gt;our
testnet&lt;/a&gt;. Further instructions can be found
in &lt;code&gt;#freenode&lt;/code&gt; there. (if you already have a certificate set, the hidden
service is at
&lt;a href="ircs://testnet67chdulhs.onion:6697"&gt;ircs://testnet67chdulhs.onion:6697&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expect the occasional interruption—even if nothing exciting happens, we still
have a few configuration things to take care of. The test network may be reset,
rolled back, or shut down at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for your patience, and thank you in advance for helping to bring Tor
access back as fast as possible!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>
