<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>freenode news</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/rss.xml</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 22:06:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>A Reminder</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/a-reminder</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the distant past, freenode fairly frequently sent /wallops about news of
conferences, releases or anything else that might be of interest to the FOSS
community. We'd quite like to do more of that, so… if you know of anything that
might fit the bill, please drop the community team a line at
&lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#103;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#112;&amp;#115;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#103;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#112;&amp;#115;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt; or message me (my nickname is &lt;code&gt;e&lt;/code&gt;) on IRC (even if the
project in question isn't (yet) registered with freenode).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'd also like to feature a bit more FOSS news on our blog, so if you're itching
to write a guest post for us, I'd love to hear about that as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 22:06:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Help protect net neutrality in the EU</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/eu-net-neutrality</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As many of you no doubt know, the European Union passed legislation last year
intended to protect
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Net_neutrality"&gt;net neutrality&lt;/a&gt;.
However, it contained
&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2015/oct/27/eu-net-neutrality-laws-fatally-undermined-by-loopholes-critics-say"&gt;significant loopholes&lt;/a&gt;
which many people believe will allow European ISPs to prioritise paying
partners' traffic. Among other things, this is potentially quite scary for
FOSS projects—most of which don't have the kind of funding necessary to enter
into such arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is something that concerns you, campaigns aimed at convincing
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body_of_European_Regulators_of_Electronic_Communications"&gt;BEREC&lt;/a&gt;
to close the loopholes are running at &lt;a href="https://www.savenetneutrality.eu/"&gt;https://www.savenetneutrality.eu/&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://savetheinternet.eu/en/"&gt;https://savetheinternet.eu/en/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2016 14:58:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AFD quiz</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/afd-2016</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As a tradition, we would like to invite our users to participate in the annual April Fool's Day quiz. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck and have fun! You can join us in #ircpuzzles for casual conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IyMjIyMjQUZEMjAxNlN0YXJ0&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">mniip</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New Website</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/new-website</link><description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this you have most probably already realised that our brand spanking new website is up and running. On behalf of freenode I would like to express heartfelt thanks to dsample, edk, Swant, thefam, emerson and SteinSplitter and boxmein -- not only for the help in designing the new website based on a very fickle and constantly changing spec but also for providing tremendously amusing banter and generally being awesome guys! You did beautifully and it has been an absolute pleasure working with you, I can't wait to do it again sometime (soon!). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and the new website is hosted with &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 23:25:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Recent Events and Future Changes</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/recent-events-and-future-changes</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many of you have been asking questions about the recent rash of high-profile
staff resignations, and we feel we owe you all both an explanation and an
apology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the explanation: in short, it's become clear over recent months that
freenode has lost its way somewhat, when compared to the ideals and goals that
we were created with. A growing sense of disillusionment amongst those of us who
remember the olden days, when we were far more friendly, approachable and
engaged in the communities we were set up to serve, has recently come to a head.
Naturally, when some of these people decided they could no longer continue with
the way things had become, it was time for us to think long and hard about what
had gone wrong and what we should do about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, to the apology. We're uncomfortably aware that freenode was set up with
the strong idea that the projects and communities which use it should be the
first, and often the only, priority. We've lost sight of that, and we're sorry.
We'll be doing our best, from now on, to get back in touch with the ideals that
made freenode such a great place.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">spb</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 13:11:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The New Policies</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/the-new-policies</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the several problems that's become obvious in recent times is that we  have too many policies, they're often not consistent with each other, and we've spent too much time and effort wondering whether something, which is obviously the right thing to do, fits with our published policy. With that in mind, the following stripped-back set of policies will apply in future, with the intention that we can set out a simple set of baselines and apply common sense on top of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nickname ownership&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicknames are allocated on a first-come, first-served basis, to the first person
who registers the name with NickServ. However, we expect users to act in good
faith and reserve the right to remove a nickname registration where we believe
that this has not been the case.
&lt;strong&gt;Nickname and account registrations expire ten weeks after they are last used.
For nicknames, 'used' means that you were using the nickname while logged in to
the account which owns it. For accounts, 'used' means that you logged in to the
account, regardless of the nickname you used to do so. Nicknames which are the
primary account name only expire when the entire account is expired.&lt;/strong&gt;
In some cases, such as for very old accounts, we may, at our discretion, extend
the expiry time of a nickname or account. We will not normally do this beyond 15
weeks past the last use.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">spb</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 13:11:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Services database purge</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/services-database-purge</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On or around Friday, October 2nd, we shall be cleaning up the services database.  This involves the bulk removal of expired nicks, channels and accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, please remember to identify to services when you connect ( /msg nickserv help identify ) and to use your grouped nicks whilst identified - remember, they all expire separately.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicks that are past the expiry threshold of 120 days unidentified on October 2nd will be freed from the database and available for others to register.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">mrmist</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 08:58:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Helping GNOME defend its trademark</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/helping-gnome-defend-its-trademark</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The GNOME project will be familiar to the vast majority of our users, what you might not be aware of is that the project is currently facing an expensive trademark battle against Groupon with the latter having allegedly chosen to infringe upon GNOME's trademark by launching a product with the same name (a POS "operating system for merchants to run their entire operation").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not going to go into the details here, as they have been explained by the GNOME project over at &lt;a href="http://www.gnome.org/groupon/"&gt;http://www.gnome.org/groupon/&lt;/a&gt; and the GNOME folk are in a much better position than me to provide more detailed information on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I am going to do is appeal for your help. The GNOME project is looking to raise $80,000 to cover the legal costs involved in defending their trademark. At the time of writing this post the freenode network has 89,998 connected users. Users who are passionate about FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 10:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Atheme 7.2 and freenode</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/atheme-7-2-and-freenode</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've begun some testing on Atheme's latest release, 7.2, and we'd like to invite interested users to help with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all changes the Atheme project has included in their new release will be included in our Atheme upgrade, so here's the bulk of the changes that will actually affect our network:&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">tomaw</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 23:18:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>User-enabled sendpass</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/user-enabled-sendpass</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As a network, we feel it is hugely important to maintain close relationships with our many communities and users. Our interactions with users in #freenode and elsewhere on the network, fielding support requests and assisting users, help build and maintain these relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we're constantly looking for things to change and make better, and one of the pieces of feedback we've had is that users would like a little automation - and the ability to be able to resolve some of their own support requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recognise that allowing users to generate their own password reset e-mails brings us in line with other registration systems online and may provide a higher quality of service.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">njan</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 21:20:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Server Issues: Update</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/server-issues-update</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Following up on our &lt;a href="http://blog.freenode.net/2014/09/server-issues-2/"&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;, we have continued to investigate the compromise of freenode infrastructure, aided by our sponsors in addition to experts in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NCC Group's Cyber Defence Operations team kindly provided pro bono digital forensic and reverse engineering services to assist our infrastructure team and have recently published a report with some of their findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nccgroup.com/en/blog/2014/10/analysis-of-the-linux-backdoor-used-in-freenode-irc-network-compromise/"&gt;https://www.nccgroup.com/en/blog/2014/10/analysis-of-the-linux-backdoor-used-in-freenode-irc-network-compromise/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Pricey</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 21:27:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Server issues</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/server-issues-2</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier today the freenode infra team noticed an anomaly on a single IRC server. We have since identified that this was indicative of the server being compromised by an unknown third party. We immediately started an investigation to map the extent of the problem and located similar issues with several other machines and have taken those offline. For now, since network traffic may have been sniffed, we recommend that everyone change their NickServ password as a precaution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before changing your password, please check your email address in /msg nickserv info and, if needed, update it - see /msg nickserv help set email (remember to check your new email for the verification key).  This will ensure that we can send you a password reset email should, for whatever reason, your password change not work properly. If you have no email set on your account or an email set that you cannot access, we cannot send password resets to you, so do please keep this up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To change your password use /msg nickserv set password newpasshere&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">mrmist</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 14:47:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New extban: $j</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/new-extban-j</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We have loaded a new module on the network which provides the $j extban type:&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Pricey</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 15:54:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>April 1st 2014, Followup</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/april-1st-2014-followup</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It's been almost too long for this blog post to arrive here after the April Fools quiz this year. Thanks to everyone who participated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first ten people who completed the challenges are, in descending order of aprilness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(times are listed in UTC)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">yano</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2014 18:05:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Heartbleed</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/heartbleed</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The recently exposed &lt;a href="http://heartbleed.com/"&gt;heartbleed bug&lt;/a&gt; in the OpenSSL library has surprised everyone with a &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2014/04/heartbleed.html"&gt;catastrophic&lt;/a&gt; vulnerability in many of the world's secure systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In common with many other SSL-exposed services, some freenode servers were running vulnerable versions of OpenSSL, exposing us to this exploit. Consequently, all of our affected services have been patched to mitigate the vulnerability, and we have also regenerated our private SSL keys and certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an unrelated event, due to service disruption &amp;amp; the misconfiguration of a single server on our network, an unauthorised user was allowed to use the 'NickServ' nickname for a short period Sunday morning. Unfortunately there is a possibility that your client sent data (including your freenode services password) to this unauthorised client. Identification via SASL, certfp or server password were not affected, but any password sent directly to the "NickServ" user might have been.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Pricey</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2014 18:52:05 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>
