<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>freenode news</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/rss.xml</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 10:05:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Spambot attack</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/spamwave</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this morning, the freenode network was hit by a fairly extensive spambot attack, the spambots were distributing links to images that 
users have reported as containing child pornography images. Naturally, we are escalating the attack to law enforcement, but we would strongly 
encourage users to be vigilant and careful not to open links from users you do not know. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would also encourage users to /mode yournick +R while the attack is ongoing so as to stop messages from unregistered users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the height of the attack, one of the klines set resulted in a utility bot attempting to ban all users connected to the network, 
I can only apologise for this and we are looking into what happened. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 10:05:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live - Opening Keynote</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/opening-keynote</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce the first of our keynotes for the freenode #live conference taking place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on 28-29th October this year. We have more keynotes to announce and these will be announced over the next couple of weeks. We also hope that you will join our brilliant line-up of speakers, and that you are considering &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/program/proposal/new"&gt;submitting a talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening keynote is a thoroughly inspiring woman with extensive experience of the various aspects of the free software communities, and we are really excited to welcome none other than the glorious Deb Nicholson to Bristol in October. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Deb Nicholson Bio Picture" src="/static/img/FNLIVEKN1-DebNicholson.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 22:52:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode at DEFCON25</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/defcon</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 15:04:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibiting at freenode #live</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live-exhibit</link><description>&lt;p&gt;You might have seen our &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live"&gt;latest blog post&lt;/a&gt;, where we announced the registration and call for participation for the freenode #live conference that takes place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on October 28-29th this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The freenode network plays host to a variety of free and open source software and other peer-directed projects. We would love to see your project come exhibit at freenode #live and we invite you to e-mail us at exhibit@freenode.live if you are interested in coming along to showcase your project and meet like-minded FOSS enthusiasts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to ensure that the freenode #live conference remains affordable and accessible to the entire community, and to that end there is no exhibition charge for nonprofits and unincorporated FOSS projects. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 09:29:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live - Registration and CFP now open</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The inaugural freenode #live conference takes place at At-Bristol in Bristol, UK from Saturday 28 to Sunday 29 October 2017. Both days will include talks and workshops, and we look forward to this community-focused gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/tickets"&gt;Tickets are now on sale and there is a special Early Bird price until 31 July&lt;/a&gt; and we are also taking &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/program/proposal/new"&gt;submissions&lt;/a&gt; for the call for participation, we have three tracks to choose from (FOSS &amp;amp; Community, Privacy &amp;amp; Security and Making &amp;amp; Remixing) and we look forward to receiving your submission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be making every effort to ensure that freenode #live is as inclusive an event as is possible and we encourage the minorities within our community to attend and to submit proposals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 19:35:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Policy Updates</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/fn-policy</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When the website was redesigned back in 2016, we made the decision to publish very limited policy for a period to allow us a chance to review our policies and guidelines, most of which were written over a decade ago. We have now completed our review and updated the &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/policies"&gt;policies&lt;/a&gt; accordingly. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 11:26:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PIA and freenode joining forces</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/pia-fn</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am incredibly excited to be able to share some amazing news with you today.
For the last few years, Private Internet Access has been a dedicated supporter
of the freenode project and we are delighted to be able to announce that
freenode is now officially part of the PIA family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;freenode has been providing services to Free and Open Source Software projects,
peer-directed projects and other projects that have a broadly licensed output
for the past 18 years, and there is a great deal of overlap between the visions
and missions of the two organisations, as well as the projects and
organisations the two organisations have supported, albeit in very different
ways over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob (lilo) founded freenode with the aim of providing a useful service to Free
and Open Source Software communities, peer-directed projects and others and I
think he would be proud of the growth we have experienced over the years if he
were still here to see it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 20:03:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Django AMA</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/django-ama</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Start thinking of tricky questions!
Once again &lt;a href="http://freenode.net/news/community"&gt;the freenode community team&lt;/a&gt;
is pleased to announce another Ask Me Anything (AMA). This time &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;
will be our guest. Read more about them in the
&lt;a href="http://freenode.net/news/django-and-freenode"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; published last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is your chance to ask Django all your questions about them:
How do they utilize freenode? How can you contribute? And just who are these
Django Girls we've heard so much about? Anything that you would be interested
in learning about them, here's your opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AMA is scheduled to take place on Wed Feb 22 18:00:00 UTC, 2017,
so grab your calendar and make sure you don't miss it.
You can watch the AMA in #freenode-ama and participate by asking questions
in #freenode-ama-questions during the session. In the meantime be sure to
visit their channel, #django, and get a head start on everyone else!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Swant</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 17:55:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Django and freenode</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/django-and-freenode</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For nearly twelve years, the &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django Project&lt;/a&gt;
has endeavoured to improve "the web framework for perfectionists with
deadlines." Django is a high-level Python Web framework that encourage
rapid development and clean, pragmatic design. Built by experienced
developers, it takes care of much of the hassle of Web development,
so you can focus on writing your app without needing to reinvent the
wheel. Of course, it's free and open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m contracted full-time by the Django Software Foundation
&lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/fundraising/#fellowship-program"&gt;as a fellow&lt;/a&gt;,
to manage some of the administrative and community management tasks of
the Django project to support rapid development of Django itself. The
fellowship program has a major positive impact on how Django is
developed and maintained, and I’d encourage any large open source
project to consider a similar program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Django community is vibrant across the globe, with many annual
conferences and local meetups. Sprints are often held at these events,
but Django’s development is mainly coordinated remotely, so good
communication tools are important to us.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Tim Graham (timograham)</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 20:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>Fedora AMA</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/fedora-ama</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="community"&gt;freenode Community Team&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce a new
opportunity to learn about one of our many groups on freenode.
Justin W. Flory (jflory7) from the Fedora project has agreed to follow-up on
his recent &lt;a href="celebrating-fedora-freenode"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; with an "Ask Me
Anything" (AMA) session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who might not be familiar with an AMA, as its name suggests,
it is an opportunity for you to ask the Fedora project all of those questions
that you have been wondering. You can ask about the project itself, how they
utilize freenode, ways to start contributing, or any other topics you might be
interested in learning more about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session is scheduled to take place on Wed Jan 25 18:00:00 UTC 2017.
You can watch the AMA in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-ama&lt;/code&gt; and participate by asking questions in
&lt;code&gt;#freenode-ama-questions&lt;/code&gt; during the session.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Nathan Handler (nhandler)</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 15:24:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New Year, New freenode</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/new-year-new-freenode</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, not entirely new but we are about to embark upon a spot of maintenance
and some minor upgrades that could cause some disruption on the freenode
network as servers are being brought down for maintenance, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to apologise in advance and further updates will be provided by
way of global notices and wallops, depending on what we deem necessary for the
interventions concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your patience and understanding while we carry out the
maintenance and thank you for using freenode!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 11:33:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Happy New Year!</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/2016-is-finally-dead</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Another year comes to an end: 2016, a year many will be glad to see the back
of. For many the year has been dominated by uncertainty, by fear, and by
sadness—a year dominated, in no small part, by the political shift on both
sides of the Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a year dominated by death. We have looked on in surprise as icon after icon
has passed away throughout the course of the year. We have looked on in sadness
as masses of people have succumbed to terror and war. We have looked on as
people try to flee, in search of a better life, often not succeeding. And as a
project based in the UK we look on as the government tries to do its best to
put an end to our digital rights, to our privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, freenode experienced a sudden influx of Arabic-speaking users.
They came out of nowhere and there were lots of them. Their arrival caused some
distress to the existing communities on the network at the time; freenode
predominantly caters to free and open source software developers and users and
we were all somewhat perplexed when our network was overrun by teenagers
wanting to chat about girls and football. They all seemed to be connecting from
Syria.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 09:46:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Celebrating Fedora 25 with freenode</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/celebrating-fedora-freenode</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Celebrating Fedora 25 with freenode" src="../static/img/celebrating-fedora-freenode.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 22nd, 2016, the &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Overview"&gt;Fedora
Project&lt;/a&gt; released Fedora 25,
the latest and greatest version of our
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_kernel"&gt;Linux-based&lt;/a&gt; operating
system. For &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/archives/fedora-announce-list/2003-November/msg00000.html"&gt;over thirteen
years&lt;/a&gt;,
the Fedora community has worked to bring the leading edge of open source
development to the world. Fedora's focus is guided by its &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Foundations"&gt;Four
Foundations&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Freedom,
Friends, Features, First&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Freedom&lt;/em&gt; is representative of Fedora's
commitment to championing free and open source software and contributing
back to upstream projects for the benefit of the open source community.
&lt;em&gt;Features&lt;/em&gt; stands for Fedora's commitment to driving some of the newest
features &lt;em&gt;First&lt;/em&gt;. Some of these examples include the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayland_(display_server_protocol)"&gt;Wayland display
server&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Systemd"&gt;systemd&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNOME#GNOME_3"&gt;GNOME
3&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps most
importantly, &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; are for the friendships made by contributors from
around the world who help make every release of Fedora possible. Part of
why &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; is an important part of the Four Foundations is
communication. Fedora community members come from all over the planet,
including six out of seven continents. The tools we use to communicate
help us collaborate, solve problems, and build friendships. IRC and
freenode are an important part of how we communicate. Fedora registered
our first channel on freenode on December 29, 2002. As we celebrate
thirteen years of open source collaboration and the newest release of
Fedora 25, the Fedora community wanted to reflect on our longstanding
relationship with freenode.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Justin W. Flory (jflory7)</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate></item><item><title>A brief security update from the infrastructure team</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/PSA-brief-update-infra</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A freenode volunteer has identified and responded to a suspected compromise of their e-mail accounts, which could have provided 
an unauthorised user with limited access to some data sent via internal e-mail systems (this could include support tickets or 
internal communications).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, we instigated audit procedures immediately so as to ensure the security of the production network and accompanying 
infrastructure. The investigation is ongoing, but at this time we have no reason to believe that any other unauthorised access 
was gained. Nevertheless, in the interests of transparency and security for our users, we wish to notify anyone who may have 
been affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, we would still recommend that you ensure that you change any passwords to freenode systems, and be alert to any 
suspicious activity on your account. We would additionally always recommend that you not share passwords between accounts, 
especially those spanning multiple providers (please ensure you have a registered e-mail address before changing your password 
so that it can be reset!).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 05:30:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode Community Team</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/community</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not be aware that freenode has a dedicated community team and that we
would be delighted to help your projects get the most from freenode. The
freenode community team consists of christel, edk, JonathanD, mquin, Myrtti,
nhandler, Swant and tomaw, and we would love to help you spread the word about
releases and launches, conferences or events and any other project milestones
that may be of interest to our shared communities. We are happy to make
announcements on IRC, reshare your social media posts and we would love for you
to guest author or co-author a blog post for the freenode website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think this is something that would be useful for your project, please do
not hesitate to get in touch with us! You can find us in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-community&lt;/code&gt;
or drop us a line to &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Swant</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 21:34:00 +0100</pubDate></item></channel></rss>
