<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>freenode news</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/rss.xml</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 12:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Celebrating Fedora 25 with freenode</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/celebrating-fedora-freenode</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Celebrating Fedora 25 with freenode" src="../static/img/celebrating-fedora-freenode.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 22nd, 2016, the &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Overview"&gt;Fedora
Project&lt;/a&gt; released Fedora 25,
the latest and greatest version of our
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_kernel"&gt;Linux-based&lt;/a&gt; operating
system. For &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/archives/fedora-announce-list/2003-November/msg00000.html"&gt;over thirteen
years&lt;/a&gt;,
the Fedora community has worked to bring the leading edge of open source
development to the world. Fedora's focus is guided by its &lt;a href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Foundations"&gt;Four
Foundations&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Freedom,
Friends, Features, First&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Freedom&lt;/em&gt; is representative of Fedora's
commitment to championing free and open source software and contributing
back to upstream projects for the benefit of the open source community.
&lt;em&gt;Features&lt;/em&gt; stands for Fedora's commitment to driving some of the newest
features &lt;em&gt;First&lt;/em&gt;. Some of these examples include the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayland_(display_server_protocol)"&gt;Wayland display
server&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Systemd"&gt;systemd&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNOME#GNOME_3"&gt;GNOME
3&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps most
importantly, &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; are for the friendships made by contributors from
around the world who help make every release of Fedora possible. Part of
why &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; is an important part of the Four Foundations is
communication. Fedora community members come from all over the planet,
including six out of seven continents. The tools we use to communicate
help us collaborate, solve problems, and build friendships. IRC and
freenode are an important part of how we communicate. Fedora registered
our first channel on freenode on December 29, 2002. As we celebrate
thirteen years of open source collaboration and the newest release of
Fedora 25, the Fedora community wanted to reflect on our longstanding
relationship with freenode.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Justin W. Flory (jflory7)</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate></item><item><title>A brief security update from the infrastructure team</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/PSA-brief-update-infra</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A freenode volunteer has identified and responded to a suspected compromise of their e-mail accounts, which could have provided 
an unauthorised user with limited access to some data sent via internal e-mail systems (this could include support tickets or 
internal communications).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, we instigated audit procedures immediately so as to ensure the security of the production network and accompanying 
infrastructure. The investigation is ongoing, but at this time we have no reason to believe that any other unauthorised access 
was gained. Nevertheless, in the interests of transparency and security for our users, we wish to notify anyone who may have 
been affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, we would still recommend that you ensure that you change any passwords to freenode systems, and be alert to any 
suspicious activity on your account. We would additionally always recommend that you not share passwords between accounts, 
especially those spanning multiple providers (please ensure you have a registered e-mail address before changing your password 
so that it can be reset!).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 05:30:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode Community Team</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/community</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not be aware that freenode has a dedicated community team and that we
would be delighted to help your projects get the most from freenode. The
freenode community team consists of christel, edk, JonathanD, mquin, Myrtti,
nhandler, Swant and tomaw, and we would love to help you spread the word about
releases and launches, conferences or events and any other project milestones
that may be of interest to our shared communities. We are happy to make
announcements on IRC, reshare your social media posts and we would love for you
to guest author or co-author a blog post for the freenode website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think this is something that would be useful for your project, please do
not hesitate to get in touch with us! You can find us in &lt;code&gt;#freenode-community&lt;/code&gt;
or drop us a line to &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Swant</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 21:34:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>Resurrecting Tor, continued</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/tor-online</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Following an embarrassingly long period of no Tor support, we &lt;a href="resurrecting-tor"&gt;recently
blogged&lt;/a&gt; about resurrecting Tor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of today, Tor users can once more connect to freenode over Tor; the hidden
service address is&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2016 20:18:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>Resurrecting tor-sasl</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/resurrecting-tor</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As many of you will no doubt be aware, freenode used to run a Tor hidden
service, providing anonymous access to the network. Unfortunately, this had to
be disabled due to concerns about abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We regret that it has taken some time to resolve this issue but we are now
almost ready to deploy some software updates that will allow us to re-enable the
gateway. We've made one important change: password-based SASL authentication is
disabled over the Tor gateway, so you'll need to generate a client certificate
and add its fingerprint (&lt;code&gt;/msg NickServ CERT ADD&lt;/code&gt;) over a regular connection
before connecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'd appreciate your help testing this setup on &lt;a href="ircs://testnet.freenode.net:9003"&gt;our
testnet&lt;/a&gt;. Further instructions can be found
in &lt;code&gt;#freenode&lt;/code&gt; there. (if you already have a certificate set, the hidden
service is at
&lt;a href="ircs://testnet67chdulhs.onion:6697"&gt;ircs://testnet67chdulhs.onion:6697&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 16:09:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><title>Happy Birthday to the World Wide Web</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/www25</link><description>&lt;p&gt;25 years ago—On the 6'th of August 1991—the world's first website went live,
and it's &lt;a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/TheProject.html"&gt;still there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the world wide web is celebrating silver jubilee today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine where we would've been without it. Would your project exist? Would
freenode exist?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Swant</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2016 22:06:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Reminder</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/a-reminder</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the distant past, freenode fairly frequently sent /wallops about news of
conferences, releases or anything else that might be of interest to the FOSS
community. We'd quite like to do more of that, so… if you know of anything that
might fit the bill, please drop the community team a line at
&lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#103;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#112;&amp;#115;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;"&gt;&amp;#103;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#112;&amp;#115;&amp;#64;&amp;#102;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#46;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&lt;/a&gt; or message me (my nickname is &lt;code&gt;e&lt;/code&gt;) on IRC (even if the
project in question isn't (yet) registered with freenode).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'd also like to feature a bit more FOSS news on our blog, so if you're itching
to write a guest post for us, I'd love to hear about that as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 22:06:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Help protect net neutrality in the EU</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/eu-net-neutrality</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As many of you no doubt know, the European Union passed legislation last year
intended to protect
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Net_neutrality"&gt;net neutrality&lt;/a&gt;.
However, it contained
&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2015/oct/27/eu-net-neutrality-laws-fatally-undermined-by-loopholes-critics-say"&gt;significant loopholes&lt;/a&gt;
which many people believe will allow European ISPs to prioritise paying
partners' traffic. Among other things, this is potentially quite scary for
FOSS projects—most of which don't have the kind of funding necessary to enter
into such arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is something that concerns you, campaigns aimed at convincing
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body_of_European_Regulators_of_Electronic_Communications"&gt;BEREC&lt;/a&gt;
to close the loopholes are running at &lt;a href="https://www.savenetneutrality.eu/"&gt;https://www.savenetneutrality.eu/&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://savetheinternet.eu/en/"&gt;https://savetheinternet.eu/en/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2016 14:58:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AFD quiz</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/afd-2016</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As a tradition, we would like to invite our users to participate in the annual April Fool's Day quiz. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck and have fun! You can join us in #ircpuzzles for casual conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IyMjIyMjQUZEMjAxNlN0YXJ0&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">mniip</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New Website</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/new-website</link><description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this you have most probably already realised that our brand spanking new website is up and running. On behalf of freenode I would like to express heartfelt thanks to dsample, edk, Swant, thefam, emerson and SteinSplitter and boxmein -- not only for the help in designing the new website based on a very fickle and constantly changing spec but also for providing tremendously amusing banter and generally being awesome guys! You did beautifully and it has been an absolute pleasure working with you, I can't wait to do it again sometime (soon!). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and the new website is hosted with &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 23:25:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Recent Events and Future Changes</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/recent-events-and-future-changes</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many of you have been asking questions about the recent rash of high-profile
staff resignations, and we feel we owe you all both an explanation and an
apology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the explanation: in short, it's become clear over recent months that
freenode has lost its way somewhat, when compared to the ideals and goals that
we were created with. A growing sense of disillusionment amongst those of us who
remember the olden days, when we were far more friendly, approachable and
engaged in the communities we were set up to serve, has recently come to a head.
Naturally, when some of these people decided they could no longer continue with
the way things had become, it was time for us to think long and hard about what
had gone wrong and what we should do about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, to the apology. We're uncomfortably aware that freenode was set up with
the strong idea that the projects and communities which use it should be the
first, and often the only, priority. We've lost sight of that, and we're sorry.
We'll be doing our best, from now on, to get back in touch with the ideals that
made freenode such a great place.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">spb</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 13:11:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The New Policies</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/the-new-policies</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the several problems that's become obvious in recent times is that we  have too many policies, they're often not consistent with each other, and we've spent too much time and effort wondering whether something, which is obviously the right thing to do, fits with our published policy. With that in mind, the following stripped-back set of policies will apply in future, with the intention that we can set out a simple set of baselines and apply common sense on top of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nickname ownership&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicknames are allocated on a first-come, first-served basis, to the first person
who registers the name with NickServ. However, we expect users to act in good
faith and reserve the right to remove a nickname registration where we believe
that this has not been the case.
&lt;strong&gt;Nickname and account registrations expire ten weeks after they are last used.
For nicknames, 'used' means that you were using the nickname while logged in to
the account which owns it. For accounts, 'used' means that you logged in to the
account, regardless of the nickname you used to do so. Nicknames which are the
primary account name only expire when the entire account is expired.&lt;/strong&gt;
In some cases, such as for very old accounts, we may, at our discretion, extend
the expiry time of a nickname or account. We will not normally do this beyond 15
weeks past the last use.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">spb</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 13:11:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Services database purge</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/services-database-purge</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On or around Friday, October 2nd, we shall be cleaning up the services database.  This involves the bulk removal of expired nicks, channels and accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, please remember to identify to services when you connect ( /msg nickserv help identify ) and to use your grouped nicks whilst identified - remember, they all expire separately.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicks that are past the expiry threshold of 120 days unidentified on October 2nd will be freed from the database and available for others to register.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">mrmist</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2015 08:58:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Helping GNOME defend its trademark</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/helping-gnome-defend-its-trademark</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The GNOME project will be familiar to the vast majority of our users, what you might not be aware of is that the project is currently facing an expensive trademark battle against Groupon with the latter having allegedly chosen to infringe upon GNOME's trademark by launching a product with the same name (a POS "operating system for merchants to run their entire operation").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not going to go into the details here, as they have been explained by the GNOME project over at &lt;a href="http://www.gnome.org/groupon/"&gt;http://www.gnome.org/groupon/&lt;/a&gt; and the GNOME folk are in a much better position than me to provide more detailed information on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I am going to do is appeal for your help. The GNOME project is looking to raise $80,000 to cover the legal costs involved in defending their trademark. At the time of writing this post the freenode network has 89,998 connected users. Users who are passionate about FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 10:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Atheme 7.2 and freenode</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/atheme-7-2-and-freenode</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've begun some testing on Atheme's latest release, 7.2, and we'd like to invite interested users to help with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all changes the Atheme project has included in their new release will be included in our Atheme upgrade, so here's the bulk of the changes that will actually affect our network:&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">tomaw</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 23:18:51 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>
