<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>freenode news</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/rss.xml</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 17:12:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Services maintenance and password security</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/services-maintenance-password-security</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We recently took our services (NickServ and friends) offline for maintenance to
ensure encrypted storage of the services database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this process, we accidentally started services with an empty database.
While we quickly realized the mistake, a large number of users were already
logged out before we stopped the process, receiving a message like "Account
&lt;em&gt;youruser&lt;/em&gt; dropped, forcing logout". Services were quickly restored to normal
afterwards and people were able to log in to their accounts as before. We would
like to apologize for the disruption and confusion this may have caused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, some people have used this opportunity to spread some
misinformation, claiming that "all passwords have been released". This is not
the case; there has been no threat to account security due to this incident.
Additionally, we do not store passwords in a recoverable form at all.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">ilbelkyr</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 17:12:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Updated Privacy Policy</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/updated-privacy</link><description>&lt;p&gt;With GDPR coming into effect tomorrow, 25 May 2018, freenode has made some amendments to its privacy policy to provide clarification relating to GDPR compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the event that you do not consent to our continued processing of your personal data in order to provide you with access to the service, you may drop your nickserv registration using the drop command (please see '/msg nickserv help drop' for further instructions).
The latest version of our policies can always be found &lt;a href="http://freenode.net/policies"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 23:58:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Channel moderation and channel topics</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/topic-lock</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On freenode, we have always tried to minimise the amount of policies we apply across the network to allow projects to run their project channels in ways that complement their wider procedures and code of conducts for the projects both on and outside of IRC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, a number of project channels opt to run their channels in a way that allows any user of the channel to modify the topic, and for most this is an approach that works most of the time, and ensures that updates can be announced and communicated effectively without all community members needing to be on the access list for the channel in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, the trade-off is that also those outside of the community are able to join and modify topics at will, and we are currently finding that a number of a project channels are having their topics changed to a message encouraging the users of the channel to move to a different channel.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 07:26:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live 2018 - Call for Proposals now open!</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/live-cfp</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="black belt" src="../static/img/blackbeltfoss.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jorge Oliviera from &lt;a href="https://www.jog.center/"&gt;JOG&lt;/a&gt;, 6x South Brazil National Champion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 20:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Celebrating FOSS, and twenty years of Open Source</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/foss-month</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For the last few days I (and several of the freenode volunteers) have had the absolute pleasure of spending time with a wide range of 
freenode users over at &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2018/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt; in Brussels. FOSDEM has always provided us with an excellent opportunity to catch up, not only with one 
another but also with sponsors, group contacts and others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to extent heartfelt thanks to the incredible organisers and volunteers, speakers and attendees who make FOSDEM (and other 
such events) possible, and I would also like to thank those of you who took the time to speak with us, provide feedback, thoughts and 
words of appreciation. It is nice to be reminded that you appreciate the freenode project, and that you feel it adds some value. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often find that a large proportion of our time is spent dealing with spam or other problematic behaviour, and
it is all too easy to forget that the incredibly small minority of users that create issues are just that, a minority, and that the vast
proportion of our userbase consists of amazing human-beings who collaborate on exciting, important and curious projects. And perhaps we
also sometimes forget to show our appreciation of the incredible work you all undertake within the FOSS and peer-directed project spaces. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 23:19:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Joe-Job" spam on other networks referring to freenode</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/joe-job-spam</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has come to our attention that someone is going around other IRC networks,
spamming channels with racist messages which suggest that they are promoting a
channel here on freenode, and that we are aware and supportive of such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are monitoring the situation, but there's little we can do when they're
targetting other networks, but we'd like to clarify that we of course do not
support any racist or hate-inciting behaviour, which is strictly against our
&lt;a href="http://freenode.net/policies"&gt;terms of use&lt;/a&gt;, and that the channel(s) referenced
in the spam messages are in no way connected to the spam - rather they are
innocent victims of a "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_job"&gt;Joe Job&lt;/a&gt;"
designed to disrupt them as well as freenode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there's little we can do to stop it on other networks, reporting each
individual sighting, particularly in #freenode, is of limited value and likely
to cause more noise than signal, but feel free to message a staffer (use the
&lt;code&gt;/stats p&lt;/code&gt; command to see who's available) if you have concerns, or particularly
if you are part of the oper/staff team on another affected network and want to
talk to us.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">bigpresh</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2017 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On Shadowbans</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/shadowban-fix</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It's recently come to our attention that an unintended effect of combining
channel modes allowed channel operators to set undetectable bans and quiets on
users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;freenode considers this to be, in short, antithetical to our values and approach
to moderation. While we recognise the challenges of moderating large channels,
we urge channel operators to be as transparent as possible, and believe that
users should be aware of moderation action taken against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of this, we are deploying a change to the &lt;code&gt;$j&lt;/code&gt; extban. As of tomorrow
UTC, &lt;code&gt;$j&lt;/code&gt; will ignore ban exceptions set on the target channel, seeing the same
effects as an uninvolved user checking its ban list.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 23:59:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live - even more confirmed speakers</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live-more-speakers</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, we &lt;a href="/news/freenode-live-speakers"&gt;announced more confirmed speakers&lt;/a&gt;
for the &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17"&gt;freenode #live conference&lt;/a&gt;
taking place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on 28-29th October 
this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we are happy to announce more speakers:&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">bigpresh</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 23:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live - more confirmed speakers</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live-speakers</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The freenode #live team are excited to announce more confirmed speakers
for the &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17"&gt;freenode #live conference&lt;/a&gt;
taking place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on 28-29th October 
this year, with plenty more still to be announced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the variety of speakers, talks and workshops we've had submitted, we're
pleased to announce the following confirmed lineup:&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">bigpresh</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spambot attack</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/spamwave</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this morning, the freenode network was hit by a fairly extensive spambot attack, the spambots were distributing links to images that 
users have reported as containing child pornography images. Naturally, we are escalating the attack to law enforcement, but we would strongly 
encourage users to be vigilant and careful not to open links from users you do not know. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the attacks are ongoing we have chosen to update the default umodes for users to include +R, please note that this means you will not receive messages from unregistered users and you will need to /mode yournick -R in order to allow those to come through. If you choose to set yourself -R, please be cautious of clicking on any links from unregistered users that you do not know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the height of the attack, one of the klines set resulted in a utility bot attempting to ban all users connected to the network, 
I can only apologise for this and we are looking into what happened. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 10:05:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live - Opening Keynote</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/opening-keynote</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce the first of our keynotes for the freenode #live conference taking place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on 28-29th October this year. We have more keynotes to announce and these will be announced over the next couple of weeks. We also hope that you will join our brilliant line-up of speakers, and that you are considering &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/program/proposal/new"&gt;submitting a talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening keynote is a thoroughly inspiring woman with extensive experience of the various aspects of the free software communities, and we are really excited to welcome none other than the glorious Deb Nicholson to Bristol in October. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Deb Nicholson Bio Picture" src="/static/img/FNLIVEKN1-DebNicholson.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 22:52:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode at DEFCON25</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/defcon</link><description></description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 15:04:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibiting at freenode #live</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live-exhibit</link><description>&lt;p&gt;You might have seen our &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live"&gt;latest blog post&lt;/a&gt;, where we announced the registration and call for participation for the freenode #live conference that takes place at the At-Bristol Science Centre in Bristol, UK on October 28-29th this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The freenode network plays host to a variety of free and open source software and other peer-directed projects. We would love to see your project come exhibit at freenode #live and we invite you to e-mail us at exhibit@freenode.live if you are interested in coming along to showcase your project and meet like-minded FOSS enthusiasts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to ensure that the freenode #live conference remains affordable and accessible to the entire community, and to that end there is no exhibition charge for nonprofits and unincorporated FOSS projects. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 09:29:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live - Registration and CFP now open</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The inaugural freenode #live conference takes place at At-Bristol in Bristol, UK from Saturday 28 to Sunday 29 October 2017. Both days will include talks and workshops, and we look forward to this community-focused gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/tickets"&gt;Tickets are now on sale and there is a special Early Bird price until 31 July&lt;/a&gt; and we are also taking &lt;a href="https://freenode.live/conference/fn-live17/program/proposal/new"&gt;submissions&lt;/a&gt; for the call for participation, we have three tracks to choose from (FOSS &amp;amp; Community, Privacy &amp;amp; Security and Making &amp;amp; Remixing) and we look forward to receiving your submission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be making every effort to ensure that freenode #live is as inclusive an event as is possible and we encourage the minorities within our community to attend and to submit proposals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 19:35:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Policy Updates</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/fn-policy</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When the website was redesigned back in 2016, we made the decision to publish very limited policy for a period to allow us a chance to review our policies and guidelines, most of which were written over a decade ago. We have now completed our review and updated the &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/policies"&gt;policies&lt;/a&gt; accordingly. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 11:26:04 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>
