<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>freenode news</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/rss.xml</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 17:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Changes to ChanServ regarding cloaks</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/chanserv-cloak-changes</link><description>&lt;p&gt;freenode offers &lt;a href="/kb/answer/cloaks"&gt;cloaks&lt;/a&gt; to our users, which replace one's
hostname or IP address in various places with a project affiliation or lack
thereof. Many of you will be aware that cloaks on freenode &lt;a href="/kb/answer/cloaks#cloaks-do-not-effectively-hide-your-ip"&gt;are not offered as a
security measure&lt;/a&gt; and
that various means are available to third parties to see through them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, many users acquire cloaks for security/privacy reasons anyway, and
we've taken the decision to close some of the more glaring holes in the
protection they offer. Please do note that cloaks are still not recommended
for hiding a user's IP address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have deployed the following changes to ChanServ:&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Scheduled Maintenance] Services database spring cleaning</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/scheduled-maintenance-services-database-spring-cleaning</link><description>&lt;p&gt;During the Easter weekend (April 12th to 15th) we will be purging the freenode services database. 
We periodically prune the database to remove expired accounts, nicknames and channels. Just like previous database purges we will be removing any accounts and nicknames that have not been used for 120 days at the time of the purge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We appreciate that not everyone remembers to identify to services, and we would urge you to check and, if necessary, ensure that you identify so as to not lose your account/nickname(s) during the purge if you use any that may be approaching the expiration limit (120 days) used in connection with the services purge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that nicknames and accounts expire separately and you will need to identify to all grouped nicks that you wish to keep, and don’t forget to also check any second accounts you may have for bots or similar (for the sake of your fellow community members we would recommend cycling through any nicknames with a client that is not joined to channels so as to minimise disruption).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fuchs</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 10:42:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Private Internet Access and the freenode project</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-pia-changes</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This week we learned the news of the proposed merger between Private Internet Access (LTMI) and Kape Technologies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;freenode is not affected by this merger. Kape has indicated that it will honour Private Internet Access' server sponsorship for the next six months as a minimum, and we hope that the company will continue to support the project also after this time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the freenode project is fortunate to be in a position where it does not rely on a single sponsor and we have a broad and diverse range of supporters; and the freenode project will continue being part of and having access to support from the Imperial Family Companies (formerly London Trust Media Holdings (LTMH). &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2019 18:50:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Matrix GDPR access request data overshare</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/matrix-overshare</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may already be aware that in the process of servicing a request for personal
information under the GDPR, &lt;a href="https://matrix.org"&gt;Matrix.org&lt;/a&gt; provided a user with a data
dump that mistakenly included events that user had not been a party to. We
suggest reading Matrix.org's &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/blog/2019/07/24/data-portability-tooling-bug"&gt;writeup&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the morning of 2019-08-04 UTC we were notified by the recipient of the dump
that the errant data included messages from freenode users and, in a spirit of
transparency, felt it was important to keep you informed of any potential
security issue concerning you.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Moving webchat to Kiwi IRC</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/moving-to-kiwiirc</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;after years of providing our good old &lt;a href="https://qwebirc.org/"&gt;qwebirc&lt;/a&gt; based webchat,
we are excited to announce that freenode is moving to a new &lt;a href="https://kiwiirc.com/"&gt;Kiwi IRC&lt;/a&gt;
based solution!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change will occur during this weekend (June 22nd / 23rd).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fuchs, ilbelkyr</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 20:42:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ircd-seven 1.1.8</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/seven-118</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're preparing to release version 1.1.8 of ircd-seven and deploy it to the
production network over the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release incorporates a number of user-facing changes:&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 10:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode Next Gen Tor Hidden Service</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/torv3</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, the Tor Project has developed a &lt;a href="https://trac.torproject.org/projects/tor/wiki/doc/NextGenOnions"&gt;new Tor Hidden
Services protocol&lt;/a&gt;.
It has a few improvements over the previous version, including better
cryptography using SHA3 and ed25519.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've added a new Tor Hidden Service address to &lt;a href="https://freenode.net/kb/answer/chat#accessing-freenode-via-tor"&gt;our instructions for connecting
to freenode via Tor&lt;/a&gt;
that uses the new protocol. The new address is&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">dax</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live 2018 is a wrap, thank YOU!</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/live-2018</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Wow. What an incredible weekend. I want to express my heartfelt thanks to all those who joined us for freenode #live this weekend. Whether you participated in person or tuned into the livestream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were fortunate enough to have an exceptionally inspiring and engaging speaker line-up - thank you so much for coming to inspire the community. Thank you also to our supportive sponsors who have enabled us to put this event on again, and of course the freenode volunteer team - both those who detached for a weekend to throw themselves into an entirely different type of volunteering and those who stayed behind to keep the network running and also doubled as livestream monitors, a special thank you to you all for your willingness to adapt and get stuck in. A huge thank you also to the venue staff, and to the AV technicians! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YOU are freenode.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2018 22:59:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Did you hear? freenode #live is coming to town!</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/live</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A little over a month from now, the second freenode #live will take place at We The Curious in Bristol. With talks from many free and open source community leaders such as Leslie Hawthorn, VM Brasseur, Chris Lamb and Bradley Kuhn, freenode #live once again brings an international free software gathering to the South West. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other exhibitors at this year’s event will be the returning main sponsor, &lt;a href="https://www.privateinternetaccess.com/pages/buy-vpn/freend/"&gt;Private Internet Access&lt;/a&gt;, as well as the Free Software Foundation, OpenSuSE, Minetest, Linux Journal and the Handshake Project. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://handshake.org"&gt;Handshake&lt;/a&gt; is a new decentralized alternative DNS root, and for a short time before launch freenode users and members of the free and open source community are encouraged to sign up today at Handshake.org and receive free Handshake coins that can be used to purchase domain names when Handshake launches in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">mattl from Handshake</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 16:47:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spam filtering</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/spamfilter</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As most of you are aware, we've been experiencing significant spam over the
past few weeks. As a result, we have decided to roll out a server-side spam
filter. Unlike our current spam-mitigating techniques, this system applies to
private messages and does not let the first matching line get through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various ethical concerns have been raised over the course of introducing this
feature. They'll be addressed below. The short version, though, is that the
system has various limitations built in designed to prevent operator abuse.
Only a tiny bit of information can get out of the filters, and they do not have
access to much information themselves, to the extent that we believe the
obvious ways to abuse such a feature are impractical.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">edk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 17:47:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Continued and persistent spambot attack and clarification</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/spam-shake</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As you may be aware there has been a prolonged spambot attack directed at freenode (and other IRC networks) in recent weeks, targeting a number of individuals involved with freenode and the wider IRC communities. The freenode team, and people involved with the wider IRC communities, are working hard to mitigate and reduce the spam that hits your community channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spam content has changed in the last few days and while I am extremely glad that the attacks appear to no longer focus on members of the volunteer team and no longer involve libellous and false statements relating to these volunteers, we feel we should provide some clarification on some of the claims that are being made in the current spamwave relating to freenode and its involvement in Handshake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current spambot attacks state that freenode is involved with an 'ICO scam' relating to the &lt;a href="https://handshake.org"&gt;Handshake&lt;/a&gt; project. Most freenode volunteers have involvement with one or several FOSS projects, often projects that use the freenode network as part of their communications toolbox. Handshake is no different in this regard, as it is a project that I have been involved with. I am deeply sorry to those affected by the spam, to freenode and to Handshake that spammers have chosen to use my involvement as a further platform to attack the freenode communities, and now also Handshake. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Current spambot attack on freenode (and elsewhere)</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/spambot-attack</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many of you will have noticed that over the last few days there has been an extensive spambot wave on freenode, and on other networks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fairly aggressive spambot attacks link to websites that we believe to have been set up to impersonate freenode volunteers, and that we believe to contain offensive and incorrect information intended to defame and libel members of the freenode volunteer team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, the matter has been escalated to law enforcement and both the project and the individual volunteers concerned have sought legal advice in connection with the current attack. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode #live 2018: Welcoming (some of) this year's keynote speakers</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-live-keynotes</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It is with a great deal of excitement that I can announce some of this year's keynote speakers for freenode #live. The entire freenode team is excited to be welcoming the following FOSS rockstars to Bristol this November; Bradley Kuhn, Chris Lamb, Kyle Rankin, Leslie Hawthorn and VM Brasseur. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a few more exciting announcements to make in the lead-up to the conference! You don't want to miss out, and we encourage you to head over to https://freenode.live to get your tickets for this year's event! And if you want to join this year's speaker line-up then you still have some time, the CFP is open and we're looking forward to hearing from you.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2018 13:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode Security Update: Reused Password Attack</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/security-update-rpa</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In the very early hours of today (Friday 29 June 2018), we became aware of unauthorised attempts to access a substantial number of freenode accounts. This appears to be the result of an attacker using lists of usernames and passwords from other online services that have previously been compromised, and trying these combinations on freenode accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our investigations commenced immediately and we found that the attacker had been able to log in to a number of freenode accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;freenode has not been hacked or compromised.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 08:08:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>freenode and irc.com</title><link>https://freenode.net/news/freenode-irccom</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In light of the two ongoing threads on &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=17375831"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/irc/comments/8t2wcq/irccom_acquired_by_london_trust_media_plans_for_a/"&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; concerning LTMH and irc.com, we have had a fair few freenode users contact us with questions as to whether irc.com will replace and/or absorb freenode, and what impact it would have on freenode communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make sure that I addressed these concerns, and I can assure you that there are no plans on the part of freenode or LTM that involve any changes to freenode, freenode is not on the brink of shutdown — if anything, we are excited to be celebrating our 20th anniversary at this year's &lt;a href="https://freenode.live"&gt;freenode #live&lt;/a&gt; event, and we hope to see at least another 20 after that. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The freenode project exists to support the development and use of Free and Open Source Software, and to that end it serves a very different purpose to the one that the visionaries behind irc.com have in mind. I fully believe that freenode and irc.com can co-exist, just as we co-exist with the numerous other IRC networks out there, and I would like to hope that irc.com may encourage those of their users who would be a good fit for freenode to come check us out, just as I hope that we may be able to send someone their way should we come across users who have great potential for running a series of training sessions or similar.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">christel</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 21:20:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>
